Robert W. Searle Papers
Robert W. Searle Papers
1918-1967
Searle, Robert Wyckoff, 1894-
9.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American clergyman; editor of Protestant world. Minister in the Reformed Church in America. Collection contains correspondence (1918-1965); records of the Protestant Council of the City of New York; articles, editorials, sermons, and speeches; appointment books (1935-1958); clippings (1934-1958); photographs; and scrapbooks.
149574
Biographical History
Robert Searle (1894-1967) was an American clergyman and minister in the Reformed Church in America. He was also an author of several books and collections of sermons, and the editor of Protestant World.
Robert Wyckoff Searle was born in New Brunswick, New Jersey in 1894. He graduated from Rutgers College in 1915, then went to the New Brunswick Theological Seminary of the Reformed Church of America, later receiving his doctorate from Rutgers in 1929. Mr. Searle was a pastor for thirteen years in three different churches: the Fort Washington Collegiate Church, New York City, the First Reformed Church, Albany, and finally the Madison Avenue Presbyterian Church, New York City.
Searle became General Secretary of the Greater New York Federation of Churches in 1934 and Director of Community Relations for the Protestant Council of New York City in 1941. Later he was appointed editor of the Protestant World newspaper. Searle was active in many civic and religious organizations that promoted social, legal, and political reforms.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Robert Searle Papers consist of seven series. The Biographical series gives an account of Dr. Searle's life from 1894 to 1945. Correspondence covers the years 1918 to 1965 and includes business letters as well as those of gratitude for his sermons and radio broadcasts. There are items in Professional career that cover practically every area Dr. Searle worked on, including bulletins and programs for speaking engagements. Writings consist of assorted forms: articles, speeches, sermons, editorials, and books, essentially on religious topics. In addition, Printed material has some addresses, etc. while Published material has newsclippings, pamphlets, and volumes-both series having assorted subjects, Finally the last section, Memorabilia, contains photographs, datebooks, and other personal items.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; Religion and philosophy; Activism and social reform; Searle, Robert Wyckoff, 1894-; Protestant Council of the City of New York.; Reformed Church in America.; Christianity -- United States.; Christianity -- 20th century.; Christianity and politics.; Clergy -- United States.; Clergy as authors.; Sermons, American.; Christian sociology.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Editorials.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sermons.; Speeches (documents); Clergy.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Helen Searle, 1968.
Inventory
- Biographical
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Business and thank-you letters, 1918-1965; undated; 5 folders (Box 1)
- Professional career
  - Controversial Issues
    - Anti-Semitism (Box 1)
    - Catholicism (Box 1)
    - Material on atomic energy and Armenian appeal (Box 1)
  - Florida Chain of Mission Assemblies, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Invitations (Box 1)
  - National Conferences
    - Chautaqua Denominational, Green Lake, Silver Bay (Box 1)
  - Positions Held
    - Army (World War I), 1918-1919 (Box 1)
    - General Secretary of the Greater New York Federation of Churches, 1934; 1936-1947,; undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Home Term Court, miscellaneous; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1939-1953; speeches (Box 2)
    - Pastorates
      - First Church in Albany, 1929-1968 (Box 2)
      - Madison Avenue Presbyterian Church, 1930-1961; undated (Box 2)
    - Protestant Council
      - Annual Report, 1946 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence with Bishop Charles Gilbert, 1939-1950 (Box 2)
      - Luncheon Honoring Dr. Searle, 1950 (Box 2)
      - Writings, invitations, etc. (Box 3)
  - Sermons
    - Church bulletins (Box 3)
    - Individual churches, 1938-1963; undated; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Union services, 1938-1962; undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Spanish controversy (Box 3)
  - Speeches, sermons, etc., bulletins, programs and letters
    - Colleges and schools, 1938-1949; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Conferences and organizations, 1938-1967; undated; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Rutgers College, 1925-1966; undated (Box 3)
  - World's Fair, 1939-1940 (Box 4)
- Writings
  - Addresses, religious topics
    - Handwritten, 1925; 1928-1929,; 1943,; undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Typescripts, 1928; 1933,; 1935-1943,; 1945-1947,; 1949,; 1953,; undated; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Articles, stories, assorted topics
    - Handwritten copies (Box 4)
    - Typescripts (Box 4)
    - Published, 1936-1947; undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - "Religion and Power", included in the book Best Sermons (Box 4)
  - Books
    - Author of Liberty
      - Published edition, 2 volumes (Box 4)
      - Publicity (Box 4)
    - City Shadows
      - Published edition, 2 volumes (Box 5)
      - Publicity (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous publicity (Box 5)
  - Books edited by Robert W. Searle
    - Contemporary Religious Thinking (Box 5)
  - Books, unpublished
    - "Science and Religion", 3 chapters
      - "Goals" (Box 5)
      - "Individual" (Box 5)
      - "Strategy" (Box 5)
    - Notes and typescripts (Box 5)
  - Editorials
    - Metropolitan Church Life, etc., 1934-1952 (Box 5)
    - The Protestant World, 1951-1952; 58 issues (Oversize 2)
  - Newsclippings, pamphlets, poems
    - Miscellaneous, 1948-1949; 1955-1958 (Box 5)
  - Radio broadcasts
    - Publicity (Box 5)
    - Typescripts, etc., 1924; 1938,; 1940,; 1942-1943,; 1945-1946,; 1950,; undated (Box 5)
  - Sermons
    - Assorted topics, undated; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Assorted topics, 1928; 1930,; 1932-1933,; undated; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Speeches
    - Assorted topics, 1938; 1942-1943,; 1945,; undated; typescripts, etc. (Box 6)
    - The Protestant World, 1949; 1951-1952 (Box 6)
- Printed material
  - Addresses and a presentation, 1949; undated (Box 6)
- Published material
  - New York World's Fair, 1939 (Oversize 2)
  - Newsclippings, 1934-1958; undated; 8 folders (Box 6)
  - Reference material
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 7)
    - Pamphlets (Box 7)
    - Pamphlets, studies, reports, 11 volumes (Box 7)
- Memorabilia
  - Date books, 1935-1950; 1953-1958; 17 volumes (Box 7)
  - Honors
    - Member of Theological Seminary of the Reformed Church, 1921 (Oversize 1)
    - Certificate of Ordination, Reformed Church in America, 1921 (Oversize 1)
    - Certificate of Appreciation, Kiwanis Club of Ossining, N.Y. Inc., 1952 (Oversize 1)
    - Certificate of Golf Prowess, Canada Dry Hole in One Club, 1928 (Oversize 1)
    - Selective Service Medal, Congress of the United States, 1940 (Oversize 1)
    - Member, Mayor's Commission on Displaced Persons, Mayor of City of New York, 1949 (Oversize 1)
    - Basketball Letter Certificate (Rutgers College) (Oversize 2)
    - Football Letter Certificate (Rutgers College) (Oversize 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Photographs
    - Childhood and youth (Rutgers Preparatory) (Box 7)
    - College and Army (Box 7)
    - Searle family (Box 7)
  - Rutgers College, 1 folder + 10 volumes (Box 8)
  - Scrapbooks, 3 volumes (Box 8)